Guide to the William Smith Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Smith papers
1760-1823
OSB MSS 57
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
The papers consist of letters, poems by both William Smith and others, newspaper clippings and other material related to Smith's career in the theater and his life in retirement after 1788. The letters discuss personal news, requests for theater tickets, inquiries after Smith's health, and other matters. Letters by Thomas Coutts offer his opinion on various aspiring actors and gossip about theatrical personages; William Dolben's letters include drafts of epilogues and odes; Capel Lofft's letters contain comments on Garrick and Roscius. Edmund Kean's letter discusses his performances of Richard III. Other papers include a list of characters performed by Smith at Drury Lane, 1753-88; his farewell address from there, 1788; miscellaneous verses; and memorabilia of David Garrick.
Smith, William, 1730-1819
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WILLIAM SMITH (1730?-1819)
William Smith, known during his theatrical career as "Gentleman" Smith, was born in London, educated at Eton, and admitted to St. John's College, Cambridge. In 1767, after leaving Cambridge following an incident during which he drew a pistol on the proctor, Smith returned to London, became a pupil of Spranger Barry, and made his first appearance as the title hero in Nathaniel Lee's Theodosius at Covent Garden in January, 1753. In the following year Smith married Elizabeth Montagu Courtenay, the second daughter of viscount Hinchingbroke and sister of the fourth Earl of Sandwich. The family objected strongly to the match, and Smith reportedly offered to retire from acting were he guaranteed an annuity equal to his earnings. Elizabeth Smith died in 1762; Smith subsequently married a widow named Margaret.
In the spring of 1774, Smith ended his career at Covent Garden in the role of Macbeth, announcing his intention to retire and to devote himself to a country life in Bury St. Edmunds. Instead, he went to Paris with Mrs. Hartley, who had been playing opposite him as Lady Macbeth. Several months later he returned to England and to his second wife, and joined Garrick's Drury Lane Theatre. He appeared there until his retirement in 1788, winning particular fame for his interpretation of Charles Surface in Sheridan's School for Scandal, a role he originated.
Upon retiring, Smith did settle at Bury St. Edmunds, returning to the stage only once, to perform Charles Surface in a benefit at Covent Garden. He devoted himself to fox-hunting and horseracing, and died at home in 1819.
Scope and Contents
The William Smith Papers document aspects of the adult life and theatrical career of the actor "Gentleman" William Smith. The papers span the dates 1760-1823, and are organized into Correspondence, Poems, and Personal Papers series.
Series I, Correspondence, is located in folders 1-47 and arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Retained copies of letters by William Smith have been listed under Smith alphabetically by recipient.
Letters concerning Smith's life in the theater and English theater in general include those by Sir George Beaumont, George Frederick Cooke, Thomas Coutts, Joseph George Holman, Edmund Kean, Thomas King, Capel Lofft, and Viscount Torrington. Kean's letter includes a discussion of his approach to the role of Richard III, while Beaumont's letters contain comments on the "Garrick School" of acting and anecdotes about the theater. The letters of William Dolben, Smith's schoolfellow, contain many compositions and Latin translation exercises as well as school and family news.
Series II, Poems, is organized into three subseries: "Addresses and Other Theatrical Pieces by William Smith," "Occasional Poems by William Smith" and "Poems by Others." "Addresses and Other Theatrical Pieces" includes manuscripts of prologues, epilogues and songs composed by Smith for his own performances, including his farewell epilogue and the epilogue he delivered after his post-retirement appearance in the role of Charles Surface at the King benefit. Folder 56 contains a song in honor of Nelson's victories in Egypt, "to the tune of'Hearts of Oak.'" "Occasional Poems" includes manuscripts of elegies, songs, and "The Death of Nelson--from the Greek."
Series III, Personal Papers, includes material related to the King benefit performance; a list of roles performed by Smith from 1753 to 1788; and two folders of David Garrick memorabilia, such as an invitation to his funeral, tributes to him, and copies of anecdotes concerning him.
Actors -- England; Theater -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Actors -- England; Beaumont, George Howland, Sir, 1753-1827; Coutts, Thomas, 1735-1822; Dolben, William, 1726-1814; Garrick, David, 1717-1779; Kean, Edmund, 1787-1833; Lofft, Capel, 1751-1824; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616 ( Stage history, 1625-1800); Smith, William, 1730-1819; Theatre Royal, Drury Lane (London, England)
- Correspondence, Series I
  - "A"
    - Axford, John. ALS to the Rev. Mr. Barton, Warminster, 1781 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "B"
    Scope and Contents
    Beaumont, Sir George Howland, 1753-1827
    - 1 ALS and 1 copy (in Martha Smith's hand) to John Taylor, Coleorton Hall, 1819 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Beaumont's recollections about the character of William Smith, with comments about Taylor's article on Smith in the Sun.
    - 2 ALS to Martha Smith, Grosvenor Square, 1821 Jun (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Expressions of pleasure at a book willed to Beaumont by William Smith.
    - 8 ALS to William Smith, [v.p.], 1805-07 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Series of letters with nostalgic comments about the Garrickean school of acting, entertaining anecdotes about the child actor William Betty and gracious references to many of the important men of the period. A draft of a Smith reply is on the back of the first letter.
    - Braybrooke, Richard Aldworth Griffin-Neville, 2nd baron, 1750-1825. ALS to William Smith, Billingbean, 1814 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Buccleuch, Charles William Henry Scott, 4th duke of, 1772-1819. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], 1802 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      With draft of Smith's reply on reverse. Accompanied by another ALS (1 p., [1810]).
    - Bunbury, Henry William, 1750-1811. ALS to William Smith, Keswick, [1803 or later] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Accompanied by two riddles, 1808.
    - Bute, Frances (Coutts) Stuart, Marchioness of, 1773-1832. ALS to William Smith, Naples, 1818 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Refers to her father, Thomas Coutts.
  - "C"
    - Cooke, George Frederick, 1756-1811. ALS to William Smith, London, 1801 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Concerns the acting of various plays and reflects the life of an actor.
    - Cotterell-Dormer, Clement, d. 1808. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], 1793 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Concerns plans to travel together.
    - Coutts, Thomas, 1735-1822
      - AL to Martha Smith, [n.p], 1820 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Note upon receiving William Smith's mourning ring for Garrick from Mrs. Smith.
      - 13 ALS to William Smith, [v.p.], 1791-1814 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Intimate correspondence with reminiscences about the theater and old friends, with incisive comments about young actors and political affairs.
    - Coutts and Co., bankers. [n.p.], 1823 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Statement to Martha Smith from 1820 July to 1823 Jan.
    - Cullum, Sir Thomas Grey, 1741-1831. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], [ca. 1812] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      A quite friendly, newsy letter reflecting the period.
    - Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811.
      - ALS to William Smith, Tunbridge Wells, 1806 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Accompanied by a copy of the letter from Smith to Cumberland, 1806 Mar 12. References to William Betty.
      - Lines written by the late Mr. Cumberland a short time before his death. Manuscript copied by William Smith., 1811 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "D"
    - Derby, Edward Smith Stanley, 13th Earl of, 1775-1851. ALS to William Smith, The Oaks, 1797 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - DeTably, John Fleming Leicester, 1st Baron, 1762-1827. 2 ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Dolben, Sir John English, 4th Bart., ca. 1750-1837. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], 1818 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Enclosing a Latin ode for Smith (1 p.).
    - Dolben, William, 1726-1814. 18 ALS to William Smith, Bury St. Edmunds, 1810-13 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      These letters contain many poems and Latin translations. They are accompanied by a letter from Dolben's daughter to William Smith and by a poem of Smith.
  - "E"
    - Erskine, Thomas Erskine, 1st baron, 1750-1823. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], [ca. 1806] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "G"
    - Genlis, Stéphanie Félicité Ducrest de Saint-Aubin, Comtesse de, 1746-1830. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], [ca. 1800] (Box 1, Folder 22)
      She presents her compliments and apologies.
  - "H"
    - Holman, Joseph George, 1764-1817. ALS to William Smith, Hanover Square, [1800] Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Concerns Holman's statement of grievances of chief actors and his "Tribute to respect" to Smith.
    - Hustler, James Devereux. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], 1806 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      With copies of Greek and Latin inscriptions for a monument to Tweddell in Athens.
  - "J"
    - Jeckyll, Joseph, d. 1837. Copy of a note to Mrs. Coutts (later Duchess of St. Albans), n.p., 1818 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Jordan, Dorothy (Bland), 1762-1816. 2 ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], [1800?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Refers to commemorative cup given to Thomas King; Smith has written a ballad on the reverse of the second letter.
  - "K"
    - Kean, Edmund, 1787-1833. Letter (copy by William Smith) to Samuel Whitbread, Birmingham, 1814 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Concerns "flattering paneganic" by Whitbread, and also Kean's performance of Richard III.
    - King, Thomas, 1730-1805. 3 ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], 1798 May, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      One of the letters concerns Sheridan's Pizarro. Accompanied by an address to the King, holograph, dated Theatre Royal Drury Lane, 1800 May 24, (1 p.).
  - "L"
    - Lansdowne, Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquis of, 1780-1863. ALS to William Smith, Bolton Street, 1806 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Lofft, Capell, 1751-1824. 3 ALS to William Smith, Troston, 1798-1813 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Reminiscences about the theater. One letter is in verse and is accompanied by transcription.
  - "M"
    - Mansfield, Sir James, 1733-1821. ALS to William Smith, Queen Square, [after 1802] (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Mansfield was Lord Chief Justice. Smith has used the letter to write down horse race results.
  - "N"
    - Nelson, Horatio Nelson, viscount, 1758-1805. Letter (copy) to Lord Stowell, Victory, 1805 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Accompanied by a copy of Lord Nelson's prayer, "composed while the enemy's fleets were in sight", 1805 Oct 21.
  - "P"
    - Panton, Thomas, 1731-1808. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], [ca. 1790] (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Portland, William Henry Cavendish Bentinck, 3d duke of, 1738-1809. ALS to William Smith, Bulstrode, 1797 Sep 14 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Relates Portland's appreciation for Smith's suggestions concerning some affairs with France.
    - Poyntz, William Stephen, ca. 1770-1840. ALS to Martha Smith, Petworth, 1821 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Concerns part of William Smith's will.
  - "S"
    - Sandwich, Elizabeth (Wilmot) Montagu, countess of, 1674-1757. ALS to Elizabeth Smith, [n.p.], [1714?] Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      The letter appears to be dated 1714, but refers to her Grandson, who was not born until 1718.
    - Smith, Pleasance (Reeve), Lady, 1773-1877. ALS to Martha Smith, Lowth Place, 1816 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Smith, William, 1730?-1819
      - ALS to Sir George Beaumont, Bury St. Edmonds, 1805 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 38)
        This polite letter commences their long and pleasant correspondence.
      - ALS (copy) to William Betty, [n.p.], 1805 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 39)
        With a copy of a poem addressed to Betty.
      - ALS (copy) to the Marchioness of Bute, [n.p.], 1818 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - AL (in 3rd person) to the Eton Club, [n.p.], 1808 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 41)
        Mr. Smith mittit Salutem to the Eton Club.
      - ALS (copy) to Joseph Holman, Bury St. Edmonds, 1800 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 42)
        Answer to Holman's letter concerning a statement of grievances of chief actors.
      - ALS (copy) to Edmund Kean, Bury St. Edmunds, 1814 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Letter of introduction for Doctor Malkin. The 26th anniversary of his quitting the stage.
      - AL (copy) to Lord John Townshend, [n.p.], [1800?] Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Symonds, John, 1730-1807. AL to William Smith, [n.p.], [ca. 1800] (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Enclosed are two poems by Thomas Grey: "On the election of the High Steward of the university, when the contest was between Ld. Sandwich & Ld. Hardwicke," and "Inscription for the Villa of a decayed Statesman on the sea-coast". Also a transcription of the poems in Smith's hand.
  - "T"
    - Torrington, John Byng, 5th viscount, 1740-1813. ALS to William Smith, [n.p.], [ca. 1788] (Box 1, Folder 46)
      On Smith's Epilogue, spoken after his last benefit at Drury Lane Theatre, of which Byng was co-author. Accompanied by two copies of the epilogue.
    - Townshend, Lord John, 1757-1833. ALS to William Smith, Bath, 1806 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Accompanied by another ALS (1806), discussing the sickness of C. J. Fox.
- Poems, Series II
  - ADDRESSES AND OTHER THEATRICAL PIECES BY WILLIAM SMITH
    - Epilogue to the Tempest, performed at the Earl of Sandwichs at Hinchingbrooke, spoken by Miss Courtenay who performed the part of Ariel., 1760 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Holograph, signed "W.S."
    - The Farewell Address to the Audience ... at Drury Lane Theater, 1788 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Holograph.
    - Lines written and spoken by Mr. Smith after performing the part of Charles Surface in The School for Scandal for the Benefit of Mr. King May the 18th 1798.... (Box 1, Folder 50)
      Holograph, annotated. Two copies.
    - Lines written in the Character of a British Sailor, at a Play for the Benefit of the Orphan Children of a Seaman who was killed at the Battle of Trafalgar., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Occasional Address Intended to be Spoken at the Opening Drury Lane Theatre, 10th October 1812, and Submitted to the Sub-Committee of Management for their Decision In strict conformity to their Advertisement (Box 1, Folder 52)
      On the theme "Scandat Phoenix felicior ignes". Holograph.
    - Occasional Prologue written and Spoken by Wm. Smith, Esq. on the opening of Covent Garden Theater, 1761 Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Prologue to Henry 5th at the Opening Cov: Gar: Theatre after the Death of his late Majesty, George 2nd, 1760 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - "Since 'tis the Intent and Business of the Stage" (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Song written and Sung by Mr. Smith at a Ball given at Bury St. Edmunds Nov. 1st in honor of Nelson's and Warren's victories. To the Tune of "Hearts of Oak.", [1798?] (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - OCCASIONAL POEMS BY WILLIAM SMITH
    - Bury. Jan. 25th, 1804: "Four Kingsmen lately came to town" (Box 1, Folder 57)
      Holographs (three copies).
    - Copied from some Lines written and sent to the Young Ladys Fitzroy at Euston at Xmas by W. Smith (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - The Dame of Ephesus translated from Petronius by WS, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - The Death of Nelson--from the Greek., [ca. 1805] (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Elegy. Upon the Death of Capt. Charles Kellond Courtenay, who was killed in the last campaign in Germany, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      Holograph
    - "Farewell my Dog, companion, and my Friend", 1786 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - For a Friend who enquired the State of Health of his Old Boy (Box 1, Folder 63)
      Holograph (two copies).
    - "In Winter's cold when tempests blow", 1805 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      Holograph. For God-daughter Caroline Smith.
    - Lines in affliction on my dear and best belov'd god-daughter Caroline, 1805 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      Accompanied by printed copy. Holograph.
    - Lines written by W. Smith on his late Friend Henry William Bunbury Esq., 1811 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - "Say, was my vision false or did I spy", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 67)
      Holograph, annotated "by W.S. to Sir Wm. Dalton".
    - "Siddons, accept the counsels of a Friend" (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Song. Newmarket. Written by W.S., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Waters of Babylon Paraphras'd by W. Smith, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - "When Farquhar's bold Highwayman met with a Priest", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Young Douglas. by W.S., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - POEMS BY OTHERS
    - Holographs, some annotated, 1765-1813, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 74-75)
      Included are copies of "Prologue to Mr. Panton's Opera called 'The Trial'"; "Written on the Elopment of Lady Mary Singleton"; "Fragment of a Legendary Tale found in the Library of Holland House"; and a variety of occasional verses, epitaphs, and riddles annotated as sent to Smith or as copied from newspapers and magazines.
- Personal Papers, 1798; Series III
  - Benefit performance of School for Scandal for Mr. King, 1798 May (Box 1, Folder 76)
    Includes box ticket; playbill; holograph copy of review of Smith's performance from The Star; and note by Mrs. Smith.
  - Characters perform'd by Mr. Smith at the Theatre Royal Drury Lane and Covent Garden from the 8th of January 1753 ... to the 8th of June 1788., [after 1809] (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Coat of arms of Smith of Kent, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Collection of memorabilia of David Garrick collected by Wm Smith, [ca. 1779?] (Box 1, Folder 79-80)
    Included are an invitation to Garrick's funeral, a tribute to Garrick by William Smith (holograph), an engraving of Garrick's arms, a copy of Garrick's verse letter to H. W. Bunbury (1774 Oct 5), "Mr. Anstey to Mr. Garrick on meeting him at a Friend's House" (with his reply), and anecdotes of Garrick.
  - Epitaphs and obituaries, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Geneaological and historical notes (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Inventories, 1809, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 83)
    Holographs. Includes plan of a wine cellar.
  - Locks of hair, 1794-1801 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1796, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Papers of Mrs. William Smith, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 86)
    Includes a printed copy of "Ode to the Poppy, by Mrs. Smith" and a paper pattern heart and wrapper for a remedy sent to her by Lady Cullum.
  - Printed material, 1801, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 87)
    Includes copies of "Trout Hall"; "The Pilgrim's Prayer"; and an advertisement for "Pinetti's Capital Deceptions".
  - Wrappers and franks (Box 1, Folder 88)